Now of course
you need to take care of
maintaining the information that allows you
to know where each file is. And you in this
case it's the operating system.
But you need to do the same also to keep track
of what
portions of your disk are actually free if
you have to store something new in this portion.
So how do we know what portions of our file
system are free?
I'm going to show you 2.
ways to go here. The first one is to use
again a
linked list in which you store basically the
addresses of the blocks that are free and you
use one last address to point to the following
block that contains the lists of blocks that
are free and so on and so forth, and this
can be maintained on disk.
It's similar to how you allocate files,
the only difference is that now you're filling
it with addresses that are
referring to blocks that are free rather than
already used by some file.
Or, you can use a bitmap so you can set a bit
for each block from the first one to the last
one. One means it is free, 0 means it is already
taken or the opposite depending on how
you implement the system. But let's say
the binary information tells you whether it
is
taken or not.
Now, which one is better? As always it depends.
If you have a small number of free blocks,
the linked list might for example, consume
less because a bunch of blocks
on the disk would already contain all the
free addresses.
On the other hand, if you have a lot of free
addresses, the bitmap might consume less space,
despite the fact that it takes always a fixed
amount of space, because you need one bit
for each block, the number of blocks is fixed,
all the blocks you have in the disk.
Again, be efficient in how you keep this
it's always more challenging than it looks.
At least based on how we discuss
these things in the course. So let's say that
you go for the linked list.
And let's say that for efficiency you only
keep the first block that is containing free
addresses of free blocks in memory, and the
rest you keep on disk and let's say that
the idea is to do this because you want to
get a better performance by interacting with
the memory rather than the disk, and consume
less time.
Sounds like a good idea, but you can still
end up in some
degenerate case. So here I'm just trying
to make an example to show you that, as always,
there are always tradeoffs. It's complicated
when you want to implement efficient solutions
for these kinds of problems.
And what the example shows you here is that
suppose that you have the block in memory
that is almost full of free blocks. OK, let's
say there are only two remaining.
And you compile a big program and you keep
creating a lot of temporary files and deleting
them and creating them and deleting them and
so on. So every time you delete a file, you
free space. You want to keep this
free space in this list because you could
use it later on and
so you store the free blocks here in this
free ones you exhaust this block, so you
write it to disk and you create a new one
and then you keep adding the blocks that are
free but then you have to create a file and
you need more or less the same number of blocks.
So you start consuming the ones you have in
memory. You only have a bunch of them.
Then you exhaust the block and you need to
read it back
from the disk and the same block you just
wrote, and if this is happening a lot of times
in a cycle in a small amount of time you
see that
your desire to optimize the thing actually
led to a solution that creates a lot of overhead
and a lot of writes and reads from the disk
and creation of space in memory Because
you are just unlucky and you end up in one
of these corner cases. It is just a small
example to show you things that can happen
that make this kind of designing a file system
and other parts of the operating system too
complicated.